# 佛山 顺德
Shunde, Foshan
# 我们现在要去吃煲仔饭
We are now heading for “baozaifan” (claypot rice)
# 你好 现在需要拼桌 得上二楼
- Hello, need to share tables now
- Go upstairs?
# 对
Yes
# 可以
Alright
# 在哪儿点餐呢
Where do we order?
# 上去再点
Have a seat upstairs first
# 哇
Wow
# 他们现在好像在现杀黄鳝
Looks like they are butchering live rice field eels
# 上楼点餐
Go upstairs and order
# 看一下 有什么好吃的
Let’s check it out, their goodies
# 虽然说 这家的煲仔饭有30多种
This restaurant have over 30 varieties of baozaifan
# 但是呢 咱们就选择这边比较特别的
We are going to order something special here
# 招牌的
Their recommendations
# 黄鳝煲仔饭
Baozaifan with rice field eels
# 咱们今天就吃这个了
That’s what we are gonna enjoy today
# 你好，我要点煲仔饭
Hello, can I order baozaifan now?
# 这个小的
This one, small size
# 金牌黄鳝的是45块钱 是小煲的是吧
A small “gold medal rice field eel” is 45 yuan, is it?
# 那我要一个小煲的
I’ll have a small one then
# 再要一个
And also
# 牛肉饼窝蛋的
One with beef meatloaf and egg
# 它如果双拼的话 比如说拼腊肠
What if I want to make a combo of two? Say if I add sausages
# 大约会多少钱
How much is that?
# 加10块钱啊
10 more yuan
# 那再要一个小煲的吧
Alright, one more small pot
# 要那个牛肉窝蛋的
With beef and egg
# 牛肉饼窝蛋
Beef meatloaf and egg
# 翻了几页没看到
(Went through a few pages but missed it)
# 算了直接写吧
(Forget it, order directly)
# 对 牛肉饼窝蛋拼腊肠
Yeah, a combo of beef meatloaf and egg, plus sausages
# 这个是多少钱
How much?
# 可以 要这两个煲仔饭
Yeah. Just these two baozaifan
# 可以
Yeah
# 谢谢
Thank you
# 大约多久才能做好
How long do I need to wait?
# 大约半个小时
About half an hour
# 半个小时那么久？
Half an hour?
# 好吧
Alright...
# 饿的时候千万不要来吃煲仔饭
Never order baozaifan when you are hungry
# 因为做好得半个小时
as it takes half an hour to cook
# 咱们刚才点了一个金牌黄鳝饭
We’ve ordered a “gold medal rice field eel” baozaifan
# 还有一个牛肉饼窝蛋煲仔饭
And a “beef meatloaf and egg” baozaifan
# 都是小份的
Both are small
# 还可以要中份还有大份
You can also choose medium or large sizes
# 不过价格可能就会朝上升很多，因为肉多
But they might be much more expensive, as they have more meat
# 煲仔饭呢 就是用这种小砂锅来炖米饭
Baozaifan are rice cooked in such small clay pots
# 任何材料放进去 和米饭搭配
Put in any ingredient, in combination with rice
# 煲一煲 都会变得无比好吃
Cook it, and it’s always super tasty
# （记忆中的煲仔饭）
(Baozaifan in my memory)
# 去年的我
(Me in the last year)
# 牛肉没有了 我们换成 腊肉腊肠双拼煲仔饭
Beef is sold out. We’ve changed it into a “cured pork and sausages“ combo baozaifan
# 分别是45元 55元
They cost 45 yuan and 55 yuan, respectively
# 这份是黄鳝的
This is the eel one
# 这份是腊肠的
This is the sausage one
# 煲仔饭的高光时刻到了
The highlight moment of baozaifan
# 就是当盖子打开的这一瞬间
is when you open the lid,
# 米香还有肉香形成最强气流
the fragrances of rice and meat form a strong air flow
# 直到大脑皮层
that reaches all the way to your cerebral cortex
# 与此同时呢 你还能够听到
At the same time, you can also hear
# 滋滋作响的听觉盛宴
the sound of splashing oil, which is an auditory feast
# 两者共同夹击
You are simply surrounded by them,
# 就问你—— 要不要来一碗饭
who are demanding -- don’t you want a pot of rice?
# 迫不及待地开动了
I can’t wait to get started
# 它这个米饭还是很烫的
The rice is still very hot
# 这个煲仔饭是从炉子上刚拿下来的
The baozaifan was just removed from a stove
# 锅边也是很烫的
The pot is also very hot
# 拿这个柄还是好一点
Better to hold the handle
# 得拌一下
Gotta mix it
# 因为（做好的）黄鳝 其实要咸很多
as the cooked eel is actually much saltier
# 煲仔饭的米饭不是软糯的口感
The rice in the pot doesn’t feel soft
# 而是有点稍硬的口感
but a bit hard instead
# 尤其是锅的内壁上
Especially on the inner side of the pot
# 你会发现它是焦脆的
it’s burned and crispy
# 下面的米饭都被炖成了锅巴
The rice below has been cooked into a crust
# 拌起来
Mix it up
# 我尝尝你的腊肉和腊肠好不好吃
Let me see how the cured pork and sausages taste
# 刚才偷吃的腊肉腊肠 酒香十足
We just stole some cured pork and sausage. Full of liquor-ish fragrance
# 但是可能偏硬一点 咬不动
But they might be a bit hard to chew
# 还是黄鳝比较好吃
So it’s still the eel that’s more tasty
# 黄鳝都是这种大骨头 硬骨头
The eel bones are all big and hard
# 所以说很容易 挑出来
Very easy to remove
# 虽然说 煲仔饭价格比较贵
Though baozaifan is kind of expensive
# 但是量也是挺多的
the size is pretty big
# 在大厅里 每个人都是抱着一口砂锅
Everyone in this hall is working on a clay pot
# 埋头在这儿吃
busy eating
# 每次吃煲仔饭的时候 这个砂锅比较大嘛
Every time having baozaifan… You know, the pot is big
# 我每次都是这么吃
So I eat like this
# 你会感觉到 脸就像做桑拿一样
I feel like my face is having a sauna
# 因为它这个还是有余温的
because of the heat remaining in it
# 越吃感觉脸越热
The more you eat, the hotter your face
# 花了100元，去结账
It costs 100 yuan. Let’s go to checkout
# 吃完饭 走出来 我发现门口的小姐姐
After the meal, I came out and found out that
# 一直在这个地方说
the sis at the door keeps saying
# 您好 吃饭现在得拼桌了
“Hello, you have to share a table with other customers at the moment”